精神病患者
美亞利桑那州  鳳凰城
12月11日  星期五
下午2點43分
你從沒好好吃過午飯
You never did eat your lunch, did you?
我該回辦公室了
I better get back to the office.
晚了老板會不高興的
These extended lunch hours give my boss excess acid.
為什么不給他個電話
Why don't you call your boss and tell him
直接請一下午的假
You're taking the rest of the afternoon off?
反正是禮拜五  天又這么熱
Friday anyway, and hot.
下午要是有空  我走著送你去機場嗎
What do I do with my free afternoon? Walk you to the airport?
我們可以在這兒多快活一會兒
Well, we could laze around here a while longer.
3點就該退房了
Checking-out time is 3:00 pm.
這種檔次的旅店  客人進來沒人管
Hotels of this sort aren't interested in you when you come in,
可一旦時間到了...
But when your time is up...
薩姆  我討厭和你在這樣的地方偷偷摸摸
Oh, Sam, I hate having to be with you in a place like this.
聽人家說  有些夫妻會故意
I've heard of married couples who deliberately spend
找廉價小旅店嘗嘗鮮
An occasional night in a cheap hotel.
結了婚當然想干嘛就干嘛了
When you're married you can do a lot of things deliberately.
你說話語氣  太像結過婚的了
You sure talk like a girl who's been married.
薩姆  這是最后一次
Oh, Sam, this is the last time.
最后一次什么
Yeah? For what?
這一切
For this.
偷偷摸摸  私下幽會
For meeting you in secret so we can be secretive.
你來這兒出差  和我午間作樂
You come down here on business trips, and we steal lunch hours.
我甚至希望你沒出現過
I wish you wouldn't even come.
好啊  那我們怎么聯絡感情呢
All right. What do we do instead?
寫肉麻情書嗎
Write each other lurid love letters?
薩姆  我得走了
Oh, I have to go, Sam.
下周我還能來
I can come down next week.
不要
No.
見你一面都不行嗎
Not even just to see you?
吃頓正經的午飯怎么樣
Have lunch, in public?
可以見面  吃晚飯也成
Oh, we can see each other. We can even have dinner.
但要很體面
But respectably.
在我家   對著我媽媽的照片
In my house, with my mother's picture on the mantel
我姐和我們一起烤3份牛肉
And my sister helping me broil a big steak for three.
那吃完牛肉之后
And after the steak,
讓你姐去看電影  把你媽媽的照片扣過去怎么樣
Do we send sister to the movies, turn Mama's picture to the wall?
薩姆
Sam!
好吧
All right.
曼璐  無時無刻  我都想見你
Marion, whenever it's possible, I want to see you.
任何情況  大庭廣眾也行
And under any circumstances, even respectability.
大庭廣眾聽起來像是兒戲
You make respectability sound disrespectful.
不  我說真的
Oh, no, I'm all for it.
那就要控制欲火  耐心地等待
It requires patience, temperance, a lot of sweating out.
否則  很難辦到
Otherwise, though, it's just hard work.
但如果能像現在這樣見你愛撫你
But if I can see you and touch you, even as simply as this,
我無所謂
I won't mind.
我討厭為不在的人賣命
I'm tired of sweating for people who aren't there.
我辛辛苦苦為老頭子還債
I sweat to pay off my father's debts,
而他卻躺在墳墓里
And he's in his grave.
我辛辛苦苦付給前妻生活費
I sweat to pay my ex-wife alimony,
她卻住在地球另一邊的什么鬼地方
And she's living on the other side of the world somewhere.
我也花錢呀
I pay, too.
住旅館不也得花錢嗎
They also pay who meet in hotel rooms.
過几年  債務還清了
A couple of years my debts will be paid off.
如果我前妻再婚  生活費也不用給了
If she ever remarries, the alimony stops.
我連一次婚都沒結過
I haven't even been married once yet.
要是真結了婚  你就不這么想了
Yeah. But when you do, you'll swing.
薩姆  我們結婚吧
Oh, Sam, let's get married.
行啊  想和我混菲爾威爾五金店后倉庫嗎
And live with me in a storeroom behind a hardware store in Fairvale?
很搞笑的  跟你講啊
We'll have lots of laughs. I'll tell you what.
我給前妻寄生活費  你得幫我貼郵票
When I send my ex-wife her alimony, you can lick the stamps.
我會貼郵票的
I'll lick the stamps.
曼璐  你要打消這念頭
Marion, you want to cut this off,
還是找個合適的人吧
Go out and find yourself somebody availabIe?
我正在想這事呢
I'm thinking of it.
你怎么會想這事
How could you even think a thing like that?
別誤了飛機
Don't miss your plane.
一起走  不行嗎
Hey, we can leave together, can't we?
我已經晚了  而你還沒穿上鞋呢
I'm late and you have to put your shoes on.
羅沃利老板吃午飯回來了嗎
Is Mr. Lowery back from lunch?
他陪哈里斯街投資商吃午飯了
He's lunching with the man who's buying the Harris Street property.
就是那位石油租賃商  所以還沒回來
You know, the oil lease man. That's why he's late.
你頭疼?
You got a headache?
一會兒就好
It'll pass.
頭疼就像決心
Headaches are like resolutions,
忘了它就沒事了
You forget them as soon as they stop hurting.
你有阿司匹林嗎
Have you got some Aspirin?
我有一種藥  但不是阿司匹林
I've got something, not Aspirin.
結婚那天我媽的醫生給的
My mother's doctor gave them to me the day of my wedding.
泰迪發現我吃止疼片很生氣
Teddy was furious when he found out I'd taken tranqullizers.
有電話嗎
Any calls?
泰迪打給我  我媽打來看泰迪是否打給我
Teddy called me. My mother called to see if Teddy called.
你姐打電話說要去圖森買東西
Oh, your sister called to say she's going to Tucson to do some buying
還說她整個周末不回家了
And she'll be gone the whole weekend and...
真他媽的熱
It's as hot as fresh milk.
小姐們  快讓老板給你們裝冷氣機
Hey, you girls ought to get your boss to air condition you up.
他今天發財了
He can afford it today.
曼璐
Marion,
-拿文件給卡西迪先生看看  -好的
- Will you get the copies of that deed ready for Mr. Cassidy?  - Yes, sir.
明天是我心肝寶貝的大日子
Tomorrow's the day, my sweet little girl.
不是你  是我家閨女
Oh, not you. My daughter.
我的寶貝
A baby.
明天她要甜甜蜜蜜地
And tomorrow she stands her sweet self
嫁給別人當老婆啦
Up there and gets married away from me.
給你看她的照片
I want you to take a look at my baby.
18歲啦
Eighteen years old
從小到大她從沒不開心過
And she never had an unhappy day in any one of those years.
別扯了  湯姆  我辦公室可涼快了
Come on, Tom. My office is air conditioned.
知道我怎么哄她開心的嗎
Do you know what I do about unhappiness?
我把不開心都買去了
I buy it off.
你...你不開心嗎
Are...are you unhappy?
偶爾吧
Not inordinately.
我送這套房子給閨女當嫁妝
I'm buying this house for my baby's wedding present.
4萬塊現金
$40,000 cash.
有錢能使鬼推磨
Now that's not buying happiness.
花這點兒錢只圖大家樂呵
That's just buying off unhappiness.
一般我是帶多少花多少
I never carry more than I can afford to lose.
數數
Count them!
我的天啊
I declare!
這就是我的花錢之道
I don't. That's how I get to keep it.
湯姆  直接付這么多現金不合程序
Tom, a cash transaction of this size is most irregular.
那又怎樣  買賣就是你情我愿
So what? It's my private money. Now it's yours.
為何不先安放好這筆錢
Suppose we put it in the safe,
周一早上如果你感覺好點...
And then Monday morning when you're feeling good...
說到感覺好點
Oh, speaking of feeling good,
你念叨的桌子里的那瓶酒呢
Where's that bottle you said was in your desk?
我偶爾才大嘴巴的
You know, sometimes I can keep my mouth shut.
羅沃利  我他媽太饞那瓶酒了
Lowery, I am dying of thirst aroonie.
這錢可不能放在辦公室里
I don't even want it in the office over the weekend.
周末前趕緊存到銀行保險柜里
Put it in the safe deposit box in the bank,
周一再讓他確認一下
And we'll get him to give us a check on Monday instead.
好的
Yes.
喬治﹒羅沃利私人辦公室
他一直調戲你呢
He was flirting with you.
他一定注意到我的結婚戒指了
I guess he must've noticed my wedding ring.
進來
Come in.
老板  給您文件  可以的話
The copies Mr. Lowery, if you don't mind,
我想去完銀行直接回家
I'd like to go right on home after the bank.
-我頭有點暈...  -直接回家吧  寶貝兒
- I have a slight... - You go right on home.
你老板和我正要出去呢
Because me and your boss are going out
接著喝酒去  對吧
And get ourselves a little drinking done. Right?
當然  不舒服嗎
Of course. Do you feel ill?
頭有點兒疼
Just a headache.
你該去拉斯維加斯度個周末
What you need is a weekend in Las Vegas,
那兒可是世界的樂園
The playground of the world.
我在家休養兩天就好了  謝謝
I'm going to spend this weekend in bed. Thank you.
不吃點兒藥嗎  對付頭疼可管用了
Aren't you going to take the pills? They'll knock that headache out.
藥片換不來開心
Can't buy off unhappiness with pills.
去銀行存完錢后
I guess I'll go put this money in the bank
我要回家睡上一覺
And then go home and sleep it off.
曼璐  怎么回事  你來這兒干什么
Marion, what in the world, what are you doing up here?
當然啦  見到你我好開心  一直都是啊
Of course I'm glad to see you, I always am,
曼璐  這是什么
What is it, Marion?
先停下
Hold it there.
您很趕時間啊
In quite a hurry.
對  我本想打個盹兒的
Yes. I didn't intend to sleep so long.
昨晚太困了  差點沒撞車
I almost had an accident last night from sleepiness,
于是就在這兒停會兒
So I decided to pull over.
您在這兒過了一整晚嗎
You slept here all night?
對  我說了  實在是太困了
Yes. As I said, I couldn't keep my eyes open.
附近有好多汽車旅館  您可以...
There are plenty of motels in this area. You should've...
我是說  那兒更安全
I mean, just to be safe.
我沒打算睡一整晚的  只想停一小會兒
I didn't intend to sleep all night. I just pulled over.
我違法了嗎
Have I broken any laws?
沒有  女士
No, Ma.am.
那我可以走了嗎
Then I'm free to go?
您遇到什么麻煩了嗎
Is anything wrong?
當然沒有  我像是遇到麻煩的人嗎
Of course not. Am I acting as if there's something wrong?
說實話  很像
Frankly, yes.
拜托   我得走了
Please, I'd like to go.
真的沒有嗎
Well, is there?
您什么意思
Is there what?
跟您說過了  我沒遇到什么麻煩
I've told you there's nothing wrong,
就是很著急  而您正在耽誤我的時間
Except that I'm in a hurry and you're taking up my time.
再等等  先別啟動
Now, just a moment. Turn your motor off, please.
可以看下您的駕照嗎
May I see your license?
為什么
Why?
請出示
Please.
請您稍等片刻
Be with you in a second!
-我沒心情找麻煩  -什么
- I'm in no mood for trouble. - What?
俗話說的好
There's an old saying. ..
第一位顧客總是最麻煩
The first customer of the day is always the most trouble...
我說了  不想找麻煩
But like I say, I'm in no mood for it,
我直接實在點兒  包您滿意
So I'm gonna treat you so fair and square that you won.
我有理由...
I have one human reason...
可以用我的車換嗎
Can I trade my car in and take another?
禿子頭上長虱子  明擺著  可以
Do anything you have a mind to being a woman, you will.
那輛是您的嗎
That yours?
對  車本身沒有任何毛病
Yes, it's... There's nothing wrong with it.
-我只是...  -有點兒看膩了
- I just... - Sick of the sight of it.
那您隨便看看
Why don't you have a look around here
挑輛中意的
And see if there's something that strikes your eyes.
然后我讓機械師給您做個一站式維護
And meanwhile, I'll have my mechanic give yours the once-over.
-想喝點兒咖啡嗎  我正打算...  -不  謝謝
- You want some coffee? I was just about... - No, thank you.
我很急  只想換輛車
I'm in a hurry and I just wanna make a change.
一般來講  買完二手車
One thing people never ought to be
急著走的肯定有問題
When they're buying used cars and that's in a hurry.
不過我說了  天氣好不吵架
But like I said, it's too nice a day to argue.
我先把您的車開到車庫里
I'll shoot your car in the garage here.
我為你推荐這款
That's the one I'd have picked for you myseIf.
-多少錢  -先試試吧
- How much? - Go ahead.
上街跑兩圈
Spin it around the block.
看起來不錯
It looks fine.
我的車外加多少錢賣
How much would it be with my car?
您不想試試車  考慮一兩天嗎
You mean you don't want the usual day and a half to think it over?
您真是很急呀  有人追您嗎
You are in a hurry, aren't you? Somebody chasing you?
當然沒有  說個價吧
Of course not. Please.
遇到顧客這么為難售車員真是頭一次呀
Well, it's the first time the customer ever high pressured the salesman.
大概算一下
I figure roughly
算上原先的的車您給700塊吧
Your car plus $700.
700塊
$700
您還是會花點時間講價的  對吧
You always got time to argue money, huh?
行
All right.
我希望您証明下那車的確是您的
I take it you can prove that car is yours.
我是說聯邦駕照  車輛所有權証明
I mean, out-of-state license and all. You got your pink slip...
-我確定手續齊備  -有衛生間嗎
- I believe I have the necessary papers. - Is there a ladies room?
在樓里面
In the building.
那邊
Over there.
我希望您先試一下車
I think you better take it for a trial spin.
我不想敗壞加州查理(二手車商)的名聲
I don't want any bad word of mouth about California Charlie.
我看沒必要吧
I'd really rather not.
我們就不能馬上交易然后...
Can't we just settle this and...
女士  跟您說實話
I might as well be perfectly honest with you, Ma.am.
不是我不相信您  不過...
It's not that I don't trust you, but...
不過什么
But what?
因為趕時間  看好了就付錢
Is there anything so terribly wrong
有什么嚴重問題嗎
About making a decision and wanting to hurry?
您認為那車是我偷的嗎
Do you think I've stolen my car?
不是那意思  女士
No, Ma.am.
好吧  我們進去談
All right, let's go inside.
放里面就行了
Just put it in here, please.
謝謝
Thank you.
加州查理: 見鬼了  警官
California Charlie's voice, heck, officer,
第一次遇到這樣的顧客
That was the first time I ever saw the customer
這么為難售車員的
High pressure the salesman,
警察: 有人追她嗎
Officer,' Somebody chasing her?
查理  讓我看下她的文件
I better have a look at those papers, Charlie,
加州查理: 您看她有問題嗎
Callfornia Charlie,' She look like a wrong one to you?
警察: 有點兒可疑
Officer,' Acted like one,
加州查理: 最可笑的是
Callfornia Charlie,' The only funny thing,
她還付給我700塊現金呢
She paid me $700 in cash
卡洛琳: 是的  羅沃利老板
Caroline,' Yes, Mr. Lowery,
羅沃利: 卡洛琳  曼璐還沒來嗎
Lowery,' Caroline, Marion still isn't in?
卡洛琳: 還沒有  老板
Caroline,' No, Mr. Lowery,
不過周一早上她總會晚到一會兒
But then she's always a bit late on Monday mornings,
羅沃利: 她來了馬上給我打電話
Lowery,' buzz me the minute she comes in,
給她姐打電話  家里電話沒人接
And call her sister, no one's answering at the house,
卡洛琳: 羅沃利老板  她姐姐單位我打過了
Caroline,' I called her sister, Mr. Lowery, where she works,
就是那家音樂大師音像店
The Music Makers Music Store, you know,
和我們一樣  她也不知道曼璐在哪兒
And she doesn't know where Marion is any more than we do,
羅沃利: 你最好去她家看看
Lowery,' you better run out to the house,
她可能在家  但沒法接電話
She may be, well, unable to answer the phone,
卡洛琳: 她姐姐也正打算回家呢  和我們一樣著急
Caroline,' her sister's going to do that, she's as worried as we are,
羅沃利: 我真是搞不明白
Lowery,' no, I haven't the faintest idea,
我最后看見你妹妹  是上周五辦公室里
As I said, I last saw your sister when she left this office on Friday,
她說不舒服想早點下班
She said she didn't feel well and wanted to leave early,
我允許了
And I said she could,
那是最后一面  等等
That was the last I saw, oh, wait a minute,
我過一會兒又見到她了  開著車...
I did see her some time later, driving,,,
你最好趕緊來我辦公室一趟
I think you'd better come over here to my office, quick,
卡洛琳  請卡西迪先生過來
Caroline, get Mr. Cassidy for me,
羅沃利: 卡西迪  跟你說過  那么多現金不安全
After all, Cassidy, I toId you, all that cash!
我沒有什么責任
I'm not taking the responsiblity,
卡西迪: 去他娘的
Cassidy,' Oh, for heaven's sake,
她給你當了10年差  你那么信任她
A girl works for you for 10 years, you trust her,
羅沃利: 好了  你最好來一趟
All right, yes, you better come over,
卡西迪: 我可不想4萬塊就這么打水漂了
Cassidy,' Well, I ain't about to kiss off $40,000!
我得把錢找回來  一個子兒都不能少
I'll get it back, and if any of it's missing,
錢要是沒了有她好看  臭娘們兒
I'll replace it with her fine, soft flesh!
我要抓住她  不管你怎么想
I'll track her, never you doubt it,
羅沃利: 且慢  卡西迪
Lowery,' hold on, Cassidy,
我還是不能相信  其中定有蹊蹺  我不能...
I still can't belleve. It must be some kind of a mystery, I can't...
卡西迪: 你不是去銀行查過了嗎
You checked with the bank, no?
他們不是從沒見過她嗎
They never laid eyes on her, no?
你到底信她什么  老天爺呀
You still trusting? Hot creepers!
我大大咧咧掏錢的時候她就坐在那兒
She sat there while I dumped it out!
眼皮都沒抬几下  暗自盤算著
Hardly even looked at it, planning,
甚至還和我眉來眼去
And even flirting with me!
貝茨汽車旅館  仍有空房
抱歉  雨太大我沒聽到您叫門
Gee, I'm sorry I didn't hear you in all this rain.
請進來吧
Go ahead in, please.
風塵仆仆啊
Dirty night.
有空房嗎
You have a vacancy?
總共12間  間間都空著呢
Oh, we have 12 vacancies. Twelve cabins, 12 vacancies.
高速...轉道了
They... They moved away the highway.
我還以為已經下高速了呢
Oh, I thought I'd gotten off the main road.
早料到了
I knew you must have.
誰沒事愿在這兒停車呢
Nobody ever stops here anymore unless they've done that.
不過我們沒感覺有什么損失
But there's no sense dwelling on our losses.
照常點燈  照常營業
We just keep on lighting the lights and following the formallties.
瑪麗﹒薩米爾
Marie Samuels
您的家庭地址  填下鎮名就行了
Your home address. Oh, just the town will do.
洛杉磯
Los Angeles.
1號房  需要什么服務隨叫隨到
Cabin one. It's closer in case you want anything.
就在服務台旁邊
Right next to the office.
我就想好好睡一覺  再吃點兒東西
I want sleep more than anything else, except maybe food.
沿路朝前10里左右有家大館子
Well, there's a big diner about 10 miles up the road,
就在菲爾威爾城外
Just outside of Fairvale.
這兒離菲爾威爾那么近啊
Am I that close to Fairvale?
15里  我去拿您的行李
Fifteen miles. I'll get your bags.
天啊  里面真悶
Boy, it's stuffy in here.
墊子很軟
Well, the mattress is soft
衣服可以挂在衣柜里
And there's hangers in the closet and
還有印有貝茨汽車旅館的文具
Stationery with bates motel printed on it
可以帶回家給您的朋友炫耀一下
In case you wanna make your friends back home feel envious.
還有那什么...
And the...
在那兒
Over there.
盥洗室
The bathroom.
如果您有需要  就敲一下牆
Well, if you want anything, just tap on the wall.
-我就在服務台  -謝謝您  貝茨先生
- I'll be in the office. - Thank you, Mr. Bates.
諾曼﹒貝茨
Norman Bates.
您不會是打算開車去吃晚飯吧
You're not really gonna go out again and drive up to the diner, are you?
是啊
No.
那您愿意幫我個忙嗎  和我吃個晚飯怎么樣
Well, then would you do me a favor? Would you have dinner with me?
我就一個人
I was just about to myseIf.
沒什么特別的  只有三明治和牛奶
You know, nothing special, just sandwiches and milk.
如果你能來  我會非常高興的
But I'd like it very much if you'd come up to the house.
我餐桌并不豪華  但廚房卻很溫馨
I don't set a fancy table, but the kitchen's awful homey.
-我很樂意  -好的
- I'd like to. - All right.
你自己收拾一下  脫掉濕靴子
You get yourself settled and take off your wet shoes,
我准備好了就叫你
And I'll be back as soon as it's ready.
好的
Okay.
我會...打傘來接你
With my... with my trusty umbrella.
不行  我告訴你  不行
No! I tell you no!
我不能讓你帶陌生年輕女孩來吃飯
I won't have you bringing strange young girls in for supper!
燭光晚餐  這種低俗色情的方式
By candlelight, I suppose, in the cheap, erotic fashion
來自于年輕人低俗色情的心理
Of young men with cheap, erotic minds!
母親  別這樣
Mother, please.
然后呢  晚餐后呢  音樂?  情話?
And then what, after supper? Music? Whispers?
母親  她只是個陌生人  餓著肚子  外面又在下雨
Mother, she's just a stranger. She's hungry and it's raining out.
母親  她只是個陌生人...
...mother, she's just a stranger...
男人不該隨便和不認識的女子來往...
As if men don't desire strangers. As if...
我不想再說這些令人反胃的事了  我覺得惡心
I refuse to speak of disgusting things, because they disgust me!
你明白了嗎  孩子  去吧
You understand, boy? Go on.
告訴她  我做的飯和我兒子
Go tell her she'll not be appeasing her ugly appetite
都不會讓她喜歡的
With my food or my son!
你沒膽量的話  要我親自去說嗎
Or do I have to tell her 'cause you don't have the guts?
怎么樣  孩子  你有沒有膽量  孩子
Huh, boy? You have the guts, boy?
閉嘴  閉嘴
Shut up! Shut up!
我給你添麻煩了
I've caused you some trouble.
不
No.
母親...我母親
Mother... my mother...
怎么說呢
What is the phrase?
她今天心情不太好
She isn't quite herself today.
你不必麻煩了  我真的不餓
You shouldn't have bothered. I really don't have that much of an appetite.
我很抱歉
Oh, I'm sorry.
我希望能替她道歉
I wish you could apologize for other people.
不要緊
Don't worry about it.
不過既然你准備好了晚餐  我們一起吃吧
But as long as you've fixed a supper, we may as well eat it.
服務台那里會比較暖和
It might be nicer and warmer in the office.
雨停了
Well, it stopped raining.
服務台不太方便
Eating in an office is just too officious.
后面有個小房間
I have the parlor back here.
好的
All right.
請坐
Sit down.
謝謝
Thank you.
你真好
You're very kind.
都是你的  我不餓  你吃吧
It's all for you. I'm not hungry. Go ahead.
你...你吃東西的樣子像只鳥
You... you eat like a bird.
你很了解它們
And you'd know, of course.
不  也不是
No, not really.
總之  我聽說  跟鳥的吃相一樣
Anyway, I hear the expression ..eats like a bird..
是不對...不對的
Is really a false... falsity.
因為鳥的食量很大
Because birds really eat a tremendous lot.
我對鳥的習性不是很了解
But I don't really know anything about birds.
我喜歡收集東西
My hobby is stuffing things.
比如標本
You know, taxidermy.
我想我比較喜歡鳥
And I guess I'd just rather stuff birds
因為我討厭看到野獸做成的標本
Because I hate the look of beasts when they're stuffed.
像狐狸和人猿什么的
You know, foxes and chimps.
有些人甚至拿狗和貓做標本  我可做不到
Some people even stuff dogs and cats, but, oh, I can't do that.
我想只有鳥類標本比較好看  因為...
I think only birds look well stuffed because...
因為它們會和你培養出情感
Well, because they're kind of passive to begin with.
很奇怪的愛好  很稀奇
It's a strange hobby. Curious.
也很不尋常
Uncommon, too.
我想也是
Oh, I imagine so.
這并不如你想像的花錢  很便宜的
And it's not as expensive as you'd think. It's cheap, really.
只要有針線  蘇打粉
You know, needles and thread, sawdust.
只要花錢買些化學品就可以了
The chemicals are the only thing that cost anything.
人應該有愛好的
A man should have a hobby.
這...這不只是愛好
Well, it's... It's more than a hobby.
愛好是用來消磨時間  而不是充實自己的
A hobby's supposed to pass the time, not fill it.
你感到空虛嗎
Is your time so empty?
不
No.
我經營這家旅館
Well, I run the office
打掃房間
And tend the cabins and grounds
幫我母親做些
And do little errands for my mother.
她認為我可以做的事
The ones she allows I might be capable of doing.
你和朋友們出去嗎
Do you go out with friends?
一個男孩最好的朋友就是他母親
Well, a boy's best friend is his mother.
你一生中還從未有過空虛的時候吧
You've never had an empty moment in your entire life, have you?
一個人的時候會有
Only my share.
你要去哪里
Where are you going?
我不是要刺探你
I didn't mean to pry.
我在找一處沒人去的地方
I'm looking for a private island.
你在逃避什么事情嗎
What are you running away from?
為什么這么問
Why do you ask that?
人們總是在逃避事情
People never run away from anything.
雨下的時間不長  你知道我怎么想的嗎
The rain didn't last long, did it? You know what I think?
我在想
I think that
我們都掉在自己的陷阱中
We're all in our private traps,
被它緊緊困住  沒人爬得出來
Clamped in them, and none of us can ever get out.
我們想抓住什么東西
We scratch and claw,
但抓到的只是空氣  只是陷阱
But only at the air, only at each other.
結果  沒有一點進展
And for all of it, we never budge an inch.
有時候我們根本沒掉入那些陷阱
Sometimes we deliberately step into those traps.
我掉進去了  我不在乎了
I was born in mine. I don't mind it anymore.
你應該在乎  應該在乎的
Oh, but you should. You should mind it.
我在乎  但我想說不在乎
Oh, I do, but I say I don't.
如果有人像你母親對你那樣
You know, if anyone ever talked to me the way I heard,
同我說話的話...
The way she spoke to you...
有時候當她那樣對我說話時
Sometimes when she talks to me like that,
我真想上樓去咒罵她  永遠離開她
I feel I'd like to go up there and curse her and leave her forever.
至少不會順從她
Or at least defy her.
但我知道我不能這樣
But I know I can't.
她病了
She's ill.
聽她說話的聲音很健康
She sounded strong.
不  她病了
No, I mean ill.
自從我父親死后她扶養我到現在
She had to raise me all by herself, after my father died.
當時我才5歲  對她的打擊很大
I was only five and it must've been quite a strain for her.
她不必出去工作
I mean, she didn't have to go to work or anything like that.
他給她留下了一點兒錢
He left her a little money.
几年前母親遇到了一個男人
Anyway, a few years ago, mother met this man.
他說服她蓋了這棟旅館
And he talked her into building this motel.
他可以說服她干任何事
He could have talked her into anything.
當他也死后  對她的打擊更大
And when he died, too, it was just too great a shock for her.
他死的樣子...
And the way he died...
你吃飯時不應該說這些的
I guess it's nothing to talk about while you're eating.
總之  那對她是一大重創  她什么都沒了
Anyway, it was just too great a loss for her. She had nothing left.
至少還有你啊
Except you.
兒子是替代不了愛人的
Well, a son is a poor substitute for a lover.
你為什么不離開呢
Why don't you go away?
像你一樣  去一個沒人的地方嗎
To a private island, like you?
不  不是像我
No, not like me.
我不能那樣  誰來照顧她呢
I couldn't do that. Who'd look after her?
她會很寂寞的
She'd be alone up there.
壁爐的火會滅的
Her fire would go out.
這里會寒冷得像座墳墓
It'd be cold and damp like a grave.
如果你愛某人
If you love someone,
即使你恨他  你也不會這樣做
You don't do that to them, even if you hate them.
你知道嗎  我不恨她
You understand, I don't hate her.
我只是恨她變成這個樣子
I hate what she's become.
我恨她的病態
I hate the illness.
如果你把她安置在某處...
Wouldn't it be better if you put her
是不是比較好
Someplace...
你是說那個地方?  瘋人院?
You mean an institution? A madhouse?
人們說的某處就是瘋人院  不是嗎
People always call a madhouse someplace, don't they?
把她安置在某處
Put her in someplace.
抱歉  我不是說不照顧她
I'm sorry. I didn't mean it to sound uncaring.
你對照顧知道多少
What do you know about caring?
你到那種地方去看過嗎
Have you ever seen the inside of one of those places?
他們又哭又笑
The laughing and the tears
用陰冷的雙眼觀察你
And the cruel eyes studying you.
我的母親去那種地方?
My mother there?
但她不會傷害別人
But she's harmless.
她不會傷害別人  就像那些標本鳥一樣
She's as harmless as one of those stuffed birds.
對不起
I am sorry.
我只是覺得...她好像在傷害你
I only felt... It seems she's hurting you.
我沒有惡意
I meant well.
人們總說沒有惡意
People always mean well.
他們言辭溫和  動作優雅
They cluck their thick tongues and shake their heads
建議正確  好像很優美一樣
And suggest, oh, so very delicately.
當然  我自己也對自己建議過
Of course, I've suggested it myself.
但我討厭這種想法
But I hate to even think about it.
她需要我
She needs me.
她并不是...
It's not as if she were
瘋子或者精神錯亂的人
A maniac, a raving thing.
只是有時候會神智不清
She just goes a little mad sometimes.
我們有時候也會神智不清
We all go a little mad sometimes.
你沒有過嗎
Haven't you?
有過
Yes.
但一次就夠了
Sometimes just one time can be enough.
謝謝你
Thank you.
謝謝你  諾曼
Thank you, Norman.
諾曼
Norman.
你是不是要回房去了
Oh, you're not going back to your room already?
我很累
I'm very tired.
明天還要開車  回鳳凰城
And I have a long drive tomorrow, all the way back to Phoenix.
是嗎
Really?
我在那里闖了點禍
I stepped into a private trap back there
我要回去處理一下
And I'd like to go back and try to pull myself out of it
乘還來得及
Before it's too late for me, too.
你真的不想再多待一會兒嗎
Are you sure you wouldn't like to stay just a little while longer?
只是聊聊天
Just for talk?
我很想  但是...
Oh, I'd like to, but...
好吧
All right.
那明天早晨再見
Well, I'll see you in the morning.
我會給你帶點兒早點  好嗎
I'll bring you some breakfast, all right?
什么時候走
What time?
很早  黎明吧
Very early. Dawn.
好  怎么稱呼...
All right, miss...
克蘭
Crane.
克蘭  沒錯
Crane. That's it.
晚安
Good night.
不
No!
母親  天哪  母親
Mother! Oh, god, mother!
血  血
Blood! Blood!
我試過很多牌子
I've tried many brands.
到目前為止  我用過的似乎都沒什么效果
So far, of those I've used, I haven't had much luck with any of them.
看看這個牌子怎么說
Let's see what they say about this one.
它說的那些成分
They tell you what its ingredients are
保証可以驅除所有蚊虫
And how it's guaranteed to exterminate every insect in the world,
但它沒說是不是有痛苦
But they do not tell you whether or not it's painless.
我想  昆虫和人一樣  希望沒有痛苦地死去
And I say, insect or man, death should always be painless.
我想這個牌子的品質
I suppose, this one seems to claim more and better
應該比其他的好
Qualities than lots of the others.
薩姆?
Sam?
薩姆  有位女士找你
Sam! Lady wants to see you.
小姐  什么事
Yes, miss?
我是曼璐的姐姐
I'm Marion's sister.
是萊拉呀
Oh, sure. Lila.
曼璐在這里嗎
Is Marion here?
當然不在
Well, of course not.
有什么事嗎
Something wrong?
她星期五離開家
She left home on Friday.
我和孩子在圖森度周末  那時我就沒見到她
I was in Tucson over the weekend and I haven't heard from her since.
甚至沒接到她的電話
Not even a phone call.
如果你們兩個要在一起  我不會管
Look, if you two are in this thing together, I don't care,
這不關我的事
It's none of my business,
我要和曼璐談  我要曼璐告訴我
But I want to talk to Marion and I want her to tell me
這不關我的事  然后我就走...
It's none of my business and then I'll go...
鮑伯  出去吃午餐吧
Bob, run out and get yourself some lunch, will you?
沒關系  薩姆  我帶了
That's okay, Sam. I brought it with me.
那就出去吃吧
Run out and eat it.
我們兩個怎么會在一起
Now, what thing could we be in together?
對不起  我失態了
Sorry about the tears.
曼璐出事了嗎  怎么回事
Well, is Marion in trouble? What is it?
我們一起來談談曼璐  好不好
Let's all talk about Marion, shall we?
你是誰  朋友
Who are you, friend?
我叫阿伯蓋斯特  朋友
My name is Arbogast, friend.
私家偵探
I'm a private investigator.
她在哪里  克蘭小姐
Where is she, Miss Crane?
我不認識你
I don't know you.
我知道你不認識我  因為如果你認識
Why, I know you don't, because if you did,
我就無法跟蹤你了
I wouldn't be able to follow you.
你為什么要插手這事
What's your interest in this?
4萬塊錢
Well, $40,000.
-4萬塊錢?  -對
- $40,000? - That's right.
你們最好告訴我發生了什么事  快點說
Well, one of you'd better tell me what's going on, and tell me fast.
我實在無法忍受...
I can take just so much of this...
別激動  朋友
Now, take it easy, friend.
別激動  只是你的女朋友偷了4萬塊錢
Take it easy. It's just that your girlfriend stole $40,000.
你在說什么  到底怎么回事
What are you talking about? What is this?
她星期五本來該去銀行存錢  但她沒有
She was supposed to bank it on Friday for her boss and she didn't.
之后沒有人再看到她
And no one has seen her since.
有人看到過她
Someone has seen her.
有人知道她有4萬塊錢
Someone always sees a girl with $40,000.
薩姆  他們不想控告  只希望把錢要回來
Sam, they don't want to prosecute, they just want the money back.
薩姆  假如她在這里...
Sam, if she's here...
她不在  她不在這里
She isn't. She isn't.
克蘭小姐  可以問你個問題嗎
Miss Crane, can I ask you a question?
你只是來這里而沒有其他想法嗎
Did you come up here on just a hunch and nothing more?
我根本沒想到其他事  只是希望
Not even a hunch. Just hope.
等我們查証后  我就能相信你了
Well, with a little checking I could get to believe you.
我不在乎你是否相信我
I don't care if you believe me or not.
我只想在曼璐越陷越深之前找到她
All I want to do is see Marion before she gets in this too deeply.
你有沒有去鳳凰城的醫院找
Did you check in Phoenix? Hospitals?
她可能出了車禍  或被搶劫
Maybe she had an accident, or a holdup.
不  有人看到她駕車離開市區
No, she was seen leaving town in her own car,
補充一下  是她老板看到的
By her employer, I might add.
我不敢相信  你呢
I can't believe it. Can you?
對于名聲不好的人
Well, you know, we're always quickest to doubt people
我們都持懷疑態度
Who have a reputation for being honest.
我想她在這里  克蘭小姐
I think she's here, Miss Crane.
她的這位男友...
Where there's a boyfriend...
可能并沒有在幕后操縱
Well, she's not back there with the nuts and bolts,
但她一定在這里  在市區的某個地方
But she's here, in this town somewhere.
我會找到她  我會見到你的
I'll find her. I'll be seeing you.
-晚上好  -晚上好
- Evening. - Evening.
我剛才差一點兒在那里轉彎
I almost drove right past.
我忘了把燈箱打開  我們有空房
I'm always forgetting to turn the sign on, but we do have a vacancy.
總共12間  間間都空著呢  吃糖
Twelve, in fact. Twelve cabins, twelve vacancies. Candy?
不  謝謝
No, thanks.
這兩天我已經看了很多旅館  眼都花了
Last two days, I've been to so many motels my eyes are bleary with neon,
這里是第一個
But, you know, this is the first place that
遠離塵世的地方
Looks like it's hiding from the world.
說實話  我不是忘了把燈箱打開
Well, I'll tell you the truth. I didn't really forget to turn the sign on.
只是想讓人以為這里很少人來
Just doesn't seem like any use anymore, you know.
那里本來是主干道
See, that used to be the main highway right there.
進來登記吧
Well, wanna come in and register?
不  不  你坐下  我不想麻煩你
No, no, sit down. I don't wanna trouble you.
只是想問你几個問題
I just wanna ask a few questions.
不  不麻煩  今天是換洗日
No, that's no trouble. Today's linen day.
我每周都把床鋪清洗一下
I always change the beds here once a week
不管有沒有人住
Whether they've been used or not.
你討厭潮濕  對吧  那...
Hate the smell of dampness, don't you? It's such a...
我不知道  發臭了  進來吧
I don't know, creepy smell. Come on.
你想買棟旅館嗎
You out to buy a motel?
不是
No.
你剛才說這兩天
Reason I ask, you said you'd seen so many
看了很多家旅館  我在想你可能...
In the past couple of days, I thought maybe you...
你...你要問什么
What... What was it you wanted to ask?
我在找一個失蹤的人
Well, you see, I'm looking for a missing person.
我叫阿伯蓋斯特  私家偵探
My name's Arbogast. I'm a private investigator.
我一直在找一個女孩的下落
I've been trying to trace a girl
她在鳳凰城失蹤一個星期了
That's been missing for, oh, about a week now from Phoenix.
是家庭糾紛  他們已經原諒她了
It's a private matter. The family wants to forgive her.
她并沒有任何麻煩
She's not in any trouble.
我想警察不會找沒有惹麻煩的人
I didn't think the police went looking for people who aren't in trouble.
-我不是警察  -對啊
- I'm not the police. - Oh, yeah.
我們確信她走的是這條路
We have reason to believe that she came along this way.
可能在這附近停留過  她來過這里嗎
May have stopped in the area. Did she stop here?
我們這兒好几個禮拜沒人來了
Well, no one's stopped here for a couple of weeks.
你可不可以先看看照片再作証
Would you mind looking at the picture before committing yourself?
作証?
Commit myself?
你的口氣真像警察
You sure talk like a policeman.
請認一下照片里的人
Look at the picture, please.
-確定嗎  -確定
- Sure? - Yeah.
她可能用的是別名
Well, she may have used an alias.
曼璐﹒克蘭才是她的真名
Marion Crane is her real name,
但她可能是用另一個名字登記的
But she could've registered under a different one.
老實講  我甚至懶得再讓客人登記
Well, I tell you, I don't even much bother with guests registering anymore.
慢慢地就不再拘泥于形式
You know, one by one, you drop the formalities.
我甚至不該費時去換床單
I shouldn't even bother changing the sheets,
然而積習難改
But old habits die hard.
這提醒了我...
Which reminds me...
那是什么
What's that?
旅館的標志燈箱
It's the light. The sign.
上周有對夫婦說  如果那玩意兒沒開著的話
We had a couple last week, said if the thing hadn't been on,
他們會以為這是間無人居住的舊...
They would've thought this was an old, deserted...
我也這么認為
Well, you see, that's exactly my point.
你說已經好几個禮拜沒人來過這兒了
You said that nobody'd been here for a couple weeks,
還有對夫婦經過并不知道你在營業
And there's a couple came by and didn't know that you were open.
對
Yeah.
正如你所言  積習難改
Well, as you say, old habits die hard.
有可能這個女孩是用化名來登記的
It's possible, this girl could've registered under another name.
介意我看一下登記簿嗎
Do you mind if I look at your book?
-不介意  -謝謝
- No. - Thank you.
好的
All right.
從日期查起
I'll get the date somewhere.
瞧見了吧  沒有此人
See, there's nobody.
我有她的筆跡樣本  來對照一下
Let's see now, I have a sample of her handwriting here.
找到了
Here we are.
瑪麗﹒薩米爾  有趣的化名
Marie Samuels. That's an interesting alias.
是她嗎
Is that her?
是的  我想是的
Yeah. Yeah, I think so.
瑪麗  曼璐
Marie, Marion.
薩米爾  她男朋友叫薩姆
Samuels. Her boyfriend's name is Sam.
她是否有可能喬裝打扮過?
Was she in disguise, by any chance?
要再確認一下照片嗎
Wanna check the picture again?
聽著  我并沒有對你撒謊  先生...
Look, I wasn't lying to you, Mr...
我知道  我知道你沒撒謊
Oh, I know that. I know you wouldn't lie.
時間久了記憶容易模糊
You know, it's tough keeping track of the time around here.
明白...
Oh, I know, I know.
記起來了
Oh, yeah.
那天下著雨
Well, it was raining
她的頭發都濕透了
And her hair was all wet.
說實話  照片跟她本人真是相差甚遠
I tell you, it's not really a very good picture of her either.
我想也是
No, I guess not.
跟我講一下她吧
Tell me all about her.
那晚她來投宿已經相當晚了  所以直接就去睡了
She arrived rather late one night, and she went straight to sleep
第二天一早就退房了
And left early the next morning.
多早?
How early?
很早
Oh, very early.
哪天早上
Which morning was that?
第二天早上  是周日
The...The next morning. Sunday.
明白了
I see.
-有人跟她在這兒碰面嗎  -沒有
- Did anyone meet her here? - No.
有人跟她一起來嗎
Did she arrive with anyone?
沒有
No.
她有打過任何電話或是...
Did she make any phone calls or...
沒有
No.
本地通話呢
Locally?
你跟她在一起過夜嗎
Did you spend the night with her?
沒有
No.
那你怎么知道她沒打過電話
Well then, how would you know that she didn't make any phone calls?
她很累  然后...
Well, she was very tired and...
我開始記起來了
See, now I'm starting to remember.
我腦海里正在勾勒那個畫面
I'm making a mental picture of it in my mind.
如果你勾勒某個畫面...
You know, if you make a mental picturization of something...
好...慢慢想
That's right. That's right. Take your time.
當時她...她就坐在后面...
She was... she was sitting back there...
不  不是  當時她手里拿著一個三明治站在后面
No, no, she was standing back there with a sandwich in her hand
還有她說她得早點去睡覺
And she said she had to go to sleep early
因為她還得開很遠的路程
Because she had a long drive ahead of her.
-后面?  -回她要回的地方啊
- Back where? - Back where she came from.
不是  你之前說她坐在后面...
No, you said before that she was sitting back there...
站在后面...
Standing back there...
是的  我后面的客廳里
Yes, back in my parlor there.
她很餓  然后我就給她做了個三明治
She was very hungry and I made her a sandwich
然后她說她很累就直接去睡了
And then she said that she was tired and she had to go right to bed.
-明白  她付現金還是支票?  -現金
- I see. How did she pay you? Cash? Check? - Cash.
現金
Cash, huh?
她離開之后  就沒回來了嗎
And after she left, she didn't come back?
她為什么要回來呢
Well, why should she?
我想就這么多了  阿伯蓋斯特先生
Well, Mr. Arbogast, I guess that's about it.
如果你不介意的話  我先去忙了
I've got some work to do, if you don't mind.
說實話  我介意
Well, to tell you the truth, I do mind.
如果做肉凍缺了凝結劑的話  就沒法凝結
You see, if it doesn't jell, it isn't aspic, and this ain't jelling.
就做不成肉凍  缺一不可
It's not coming together. Something's missing.
我不知道你期望我告訴你些什么
Well, I don't know what you could expect me to know.
人們來來往往
People just come and go, you know.
對  她不是還在這兒吧
That's right. She isn't still here, is she?
不在了
No.
如果我想要檢查所有的房間
If I wanted to check the cabins, all 12 of them,
我是不是需要搜查令呀
I'd need a warrant, wouldn't I?
如果你不信的話  就跟我來吧
Listen, if you don't believe me, come on with me.
你可以幫我換床單
You can help me change beds.
不用了  多謝
Okay? Oh. no, thanks.
改變主意了?
Change your mind?
我...我想肯定是因為我的某些表情
You know, I... I think I must have one of those faces you just can't
使得你不相信我的話
Help believing.
-還有人在家嗎  -沒有
- Is anyone at home? - No.
是嗎  那兒有人坐在窗戶旁邊
Oh? There's somebody sitting up in the window.
沒  沒有
No, no, there isn't.
肯定有  你去瞧瞧
Sure, go ahead. Take a look.
那肯定是我母親
Oh, that must be my mother.
她是個病人
She's an invalid.
實際上  她喜歡獨居
It's practically like living alone.
明白
Oh, I see.
如果這個女孩  曼璐﹒克蘭在這兒
Now, if this girl, Marion Crane, were here, you wouldn't
你不會把她藏起來吧
Be hiding her, would you?
-不會  -即使她出高價也不會嗎
- No. - Not even if she paid you well?
不會
No.
我們這樣說好了  我不想跟你爭論
Let's just say, just for the sake of argument,
她想要你勇敢地保護她
That she wanted you to gallantly protect her.
你知道你被利用了
You'd know that you were being used.
你不會蠢到被耍吧
You wouldn't be made a fool of, would you?
但我并不傻  我...
But I'm not a fool. well, I...
我不能被別人愚弄  即便是被女人耍
And I'm not capable of being fooled, not even by a woman.
這不是在詆毀你的男子氣概
Well, this is not a slur on your manhood.
這么說吧
Let's put it this way.
她可能耍了我  但她沒有耍我的母親
She might have fooled me, but she didn't fool my mother.
那你母親見過她了?  我可以跟你母親談一下嗎
Well, then your mother met her. Could I talk to your mother?
不行  如我之前跟你說的  她不見外人
No. As I told you, she's confined.
知道  但就几分鐘而已
Yes, but just for a few minutes. That's all.
可能會有你所遺漏的線索
There might be some hint that you missed out on.
生病的老女人通常比較易怒
You know, sick old women are usually pretty sharp.
阿伯蓋斯特先生...我想我已經...
Mr. Arbogast... I think I've...
就一會兒  我不會觸怒她的
Just for a moment. I wouldn't disturb her.
我想我已經都跟你說清楚了
I think I've talked to you all I want to.
知道  但就...
Yes, but just for...
我想如果你馬上離開就再好不過了  謝謝
I think it'd be much better if you left now. Thanks.
好吧
Well, all right.
如果你讓我跟她談一下肯定會讓我少走很多冤枉路
You sure would save me a lot of leg work if you'd let me talk to her.
這也需要搜查令嗎
Would I need a warrant for that, too?
當然
Sure.
好吧  不管怎樣還是謝謝
All right. Thanks anyway.
喂  盧密斯  我是阿伯蓋斯特  萊拉在嗎
Hello, Loomis. This is Arbogast. Is Lila there?
好  請讓她聽電話
Okay. Let me talk to her, please.
喂  萊拉
Hello, Lila.
聽著  萊拉  曼璐來過這兒
Lila, listen. Marion was up here.
是的  上個星期六晚上她在貝茨汽車旅館投宿
Yes, she spent last Saturday night at the Bates Motel.
就在舊公路旁邊
It's right out here on the old highway.
我連她住哪個房間都知道  是1號房
I even know what cabin she was in. It was number one.
這個年輕的旅館老板說她只住了一晚
This young fella that runs the place said that she just spent the night,
第二天就離開了  就這樣
Left the next day and that was it.
還不大確定
No, not exactly.
相信我  我確實盤問過他
Well, I did question him, believe me,
但我認為我這趟沒白來
But I think I got all there was to get.
我還得從這兒找點線索
I'll just have to pick up the pieces from here.
說實話  我感覺不是很滿意...
Well, I tell you, I don't feel entirely satisfied...
這個小伙子有個生病的老母親
See, this boy had a sick old mother.
我想她見過曼璐并跟她說過話
I think she saw Marion and talked to her.
沒有  遺憾地是他不讓我見她
No. No, unfortunately, he wouldn't let me see her.
我有  但我想會先回汽車旅館
Well, I was, but I think I'll go back to the motel first.
不用  你跟盧密斯待一起  我大概1小時內回去
No, you stay there with Loomis. I'll be back in about an hour.
好的  聽著  我...
All right, fine. Listen, I...
你知道我的想法會很高興的
You'll be happy to know what I think.
我想我們的朋友薩姆﹒盧密斯并不知道曼璐來這兒
I think our friend Sam Loomis didn't know that Marion was here.
好的  大概1小時左右見
Yeah. all right. See you in about an hour or less.
好的  再見
All right, bye bye.
貝茨?
Bates?
有時寂寞的聲音會縈繞在周六的夜晚
Sometimes Saturday night has a lonely sound.
有留意過嗎  萊拉
Ever notice that, Lila?
薩姆  他說1小時左右
Sam, he said an hour or less.
對
Yeah.
已經過去3個小時了
It's been three.
難道我們就這樣坐著干等嗎
Well, are we just going to sit here and wait?
他會回來的
He'll be back.
耐心等待吧
Let's sit still and hang on, okay?
舊公路有多遠?
How far is the old highway?
你不會想要出去吧
You wanna go out there, don't you?
-找阿伯蓋斯特跟那個老太太算賬...  -是的
- Bust in on Arbogast and the old lady... - Yes.
-或許搖醒她  -是的
- Maybe shake her up. - Yes!
那可不是什么理智的行為
That wouldn't be a wise thing to do.
在我的家族字典里沒有耐心兩字
Patience doesn't run in my family, Sam.
-我要出去  -聽著  阿伯蓋斯特說過...
- I'm going out there. - Look, Arbogast said...
1個小時左右嘛
An hour, or less.
我走了
Well, I'm going.
你會迷路的
You'll never find it.
待在這兒
Stay here.
為什么我不可以跟你一起去
Why can't I go with you?
不知道  我們其中一個得留下
I don't know. One of us has to be here,
說不定他已經在路上了
In case he's on the way.
我該做些什么  就這樣坐著干等嗎
What am I supposed to do, just sit here and wait?
對  待在這兒
Yeah. stay here.
阿伯蓋斯特?
Arbogast?
Arbogast!
阿伯蓋斯特?
他還沒回來嗎
He didn't come back here?
薩姆
Sam!
阿伯蓋斯特跟貝茨都不在  只有一個老太太在家
No Arbogast, no Bates. Only the old lady at home.
病老太沒法應門  或是不愿應門
Sick old lady unable to answer the door, or unwilling.
他會去哪兒了呢
Where could he have gone?
也許他找到了一些確切的線索
Maybe he got some definite lead.
就直奔線索而去了
Maybe he went right on.
不知會我一聲?
Without calling me?
走得太急了
In a hurry.
薩姆  當時他什么線索都沒有就打來了
Sam, he called when he had nothing.
什么都沒  除了一股不滿意的感覺
Nothing but a dissatisfied feeling.
你不認為如果他發現了什么會打給我們嗎
Don't you think he'd have called if he had anything at all?
是的  我想他會打來
Yes, I think he would've.
我們去見艾爾﹒錢伯斯吧
Let's go see Al Chambers.
他是誰
Who's he?
我們這兒的副警長
Our deputy sheriff around here.
好的  我去拿外套
All right. Let me get my coat.
晚上好
Good evening.
不知道該從何說起  直接切入主題吧
Well, I don't know where to start, except at the beginning.
好
Yes.
這位是來自鳳凰城的萊拉﹒克蘭
This is Lila Crane from Phoenix.
你好
How do you do?
她來這兒是為了找她妹妹的
She's been here searching for her sister.
請了一位私家偵探幫忙...
There's this private detective helping and...
我們接到那個私家偵探打來的電話
Well, we got a call from this detective
說他在那家舊公路旁的汽車旅館追查到她的消息
Saying that he'd traced her to that motel out on the old highway.
那肯定是貝茨汽車旅館
That must be the Bates Motel.
他查到她住過那兒
He traced her there
然后打給我們說他要去盤問貝茨太太
and called us to say he was going to question Mrs.Bates.
諾曼結婚了?
Norman took a wife?
不是  我想沒有  是位老太太  他的母親
No, I don't think so. An old woman. His mother.
不管是誰  自從挂完電話后
Well, anyway, that was early this evening.
我們就跟他失去了聯系
We haven't seen or heard from him since.
你妹妹失蹤多久了
Now, your sister's missing how long?
到昨天為止  她已經失蹤1個星期了
Well, she left Phoenix a week ago yesterday, without a trace.
你跟那位偵探怎么會追查到菲爾威爾的
How'd you and this detective come to trace her to Fairvale?
他們以為她來找我了
They thought she'd be coming to me.
她是獨自離開鳳凰城的嗎
Left Phoenix under her own steam?
是的
Yes.
她不像是失蹤倒像是逃跑
She's not missing so much as she's run away.
對
That's right.
為什么
From what?
她偷了些錢
She stole some money.
很多嗎
A lot?
4萬塊錢
$40,000.
那警方沒有...
And the police haven't been able to...
大家考慮到...
Everyone concerned thought
如果他們能讓她把錢還回去的話
If they could get her to give the money back,
他們可以避免她被抓進警局
They could avoid involving her with the police.
所以才請私家偵探
That explains the private detective.
他追查到她曾住在貝茨旅館
He traced her to the Bates place.
他打電話給你具體說了些什么
What exactly did he say when he called you?
他說曼璐在那兒住了一晚就走了
Well, he said that Marion was there for one night and then she left.
帶著4萬塊錢?
With the $40,000?
錢的事他只字未提
Well, he didn't say anything about the money.
電話內容無關緊要  是嗎
It isn't important what he said on the phone, is it?
在他跟那位母親談完話之后
He was supposed to come back here and talk to us
他本該回到這兒跟我們碰面  但他并沒回來
After he talked to the mother, and he didn't.
所以我才找你介入調查此事
That's what I want you to do something about.
調查什么
Like what?
抱歉我說話急了點
I'm sorry if I seem overanxious.
只是我敢肯定那兒
It's just that I'm sure there's
有什么不對勁  并且我必須調查清楚
something wrong out there and I have to know what.
我也覺得那兒不對勁
Well, I think there's something wrong too, Miss,
但不是同一件事
but not the same thing.
我想不對勁的是你的私家偵探
I think what's wrong is your private detective.
我想他可能從諾曼﹒貝茨那兒
I think he got himself a hot lead as to where your sister was going,
知道你妹妹去向的重要線索
Probably from Norman Bates,
然后打給你  讓你們繼續等消息
And called you to keep you still
而他就出發去追她和錢
While he took off after her and the money.
不會的  他說他還沒調查清楚會再回來
No, no, he said he was dissatisfied and he was going back there.
為什么不打給諾曼  問他說到底發生了什么事
Why don't you call Norman and let him say just what happened?
現在嗎
At this hour?
我剛從那兒回來  他出去了
Well, he was out when I was there just a while ago.
如果他回來了  可能還沒睡
If he's back, he probably isn't even in bed yet.
你去的時候他在家
He wasn't out when you were there,
夜闌人靜
He just wasn't
像某些人一樣  不應門罷了
answering the door in the dead of night, like some people do.
這個小伙子像位隱士
This fellow lives like a hermit.
你肯定還記得10年前發生的那件不幸的事
You must remember that bad business out there about 10 years ago.
求你打一下吧
Please. Call.
弗洛里  警長讓你連線貝茨汽車旅館
Florrie, the Sheriff wants you to connect him with the Bates Motel.
喂  是諾曼嗎  我是錢伯斯警長
Hello, Norman? Sheriff Chambers.
我很好  謝謝
I've been just fine, thanks.
聽著  我們這兒出了點事
Listen, we got worries here.
今晚是否有個男的去過你那兒
Yeah, have you had a fella stop by there tonight...
他不是來投宿的
Well, this one wouldn't be a customer, anyway.
他是位私家偵探  名字叫...
He's a private detective, name of...
阿伯蓋斯特
Arbogast.
叫阿伯蓋斯特
他離開之后呢
And after he left?
沒關系  諾曼
No, that's okay, Norman.
這位偵探去過那兒  諾曼跟他講了那個女孩的事
This detective was there, Norman told him about the girl,
偵探謝過他之后就走了
The detective thanked him and he went away.
他沒再回去嗎  他沒去見那位母親嗎
And he didn't come back? He didn't see the mother?
你的偵探告訴你  他不能馬上回來
Your detective told you he couldn't come right back
因為他要去盤問諾曼﹒貝茨的母親  是嗎
Because he was going to question Norman Bates's mother, right?
是的
Yes.
諾曼﹒貝茨的母親10年前就去世了
Norman Bates's mother has been dead and buried
并安葬在綠色草坪墓地
In Green Lawn cemetery for the past 10 years.
她被安葬時所穿的壽衣還是我幫諾曼選的
I helped Norman pick out the dress she was buried in.
淺紫光藍色
Periwinkle blue.
那不只是地方歷史事件
It ain't only local history, Sam.
也是菲爾威爾地區唯一一起謀殺跟自殺案
It's the only case of murder and suicide on Fairvale Ledgers.
當貝茨太太發現跟她交往的家伙已有家室
Mrs. Bates poisoned this guy she was involved with
她就把他毒死了
When she found out he was married.
然后她也服毒自殺了
Then took a helping of the same stuff herself.
是番木鱉鹼  死得很難看
Strychnine. Ugly way to die.
諾曼發現他們死在一起
Norman found them dead together.
在床上
In bed.
你是說我見到的那個坐在窗邊的老婦人
You mean that old woman I saw sitting in the window out there wasn't
不是貝茨的母親嗎
Bates' mother?
等等  薩姆  你肯定見過一位老婦人嗎
Now, wait a minute, Sam. Are you sure you saw an old woman?
是的  在汽車旅館后面的房子里
Yes! In the house behind the motel!
我去叫門  但她根本不理我
I called and pounded but she just ignored me!
你是想告訴我  你見到了諾曼﹒貝茨的母親  對嗎
You want to tell me you saw Norman Bates' mother?
但她肯定是  因為阿伯蓋斯特也這么說
But it had to be because Arbogast said so, too!
那個年輕人不讓他去見她  是因為她病得很重
And the young man wouldn't let him see her because she was too ill.
好吧  如果那位婦人是貝茨太太
Well, if the woman up there is Mrs. Bates,
那埋在綠草坪墓地的又是誰呢
Who's that woman buried out in Green Lawn cemetery?
母親  我現在要提出...
Now, mother, I'm gonna bring something up...
抱歉  孩子
I am sorry, boy,
但你命令我時  看起來確實很可笑
But you do manage to look ludicrous when you give me orders.
求您了  母親
Please, mother.
不行  我不會藏在果窖里
No! I will not hide in the fruit cellar.
你覺得我瘋了  對嗎
You think I'm fruity, huh?
我就待在這兒
I'm staying right here.
這是我的房間  誰也別想把我趕走
This is my room and no one will drag me out of it,
我無恥的兒子更不行
Least of all my big, bold son.
他們會來這兒的  母親
They'll come now, mother.
他跟蹤過那個姑娘  現在有人要跟蹤他
He came after the girl, and now someone will come after him.
母親  求您了  几天就好
Mother, please, it's just for a few days.
這樣他們就找不到您了
Just for a few days so they won't find you.
几天就好嗎
Just for a few days?
在這陰暗潮濕的果窖?  決不
In that dark, dank fruit cellar? No!
你曾把我藏在那里  孩子  你休想再讓我去那兒了  絕不
You hid me there once, boy, and you won't do it again, not ever again!
現在滾蛋
Now get out!
我讓你滾蛋  小子
I told you to get out, boy.
我把您抱下去  母親
I'll carry you, mother.
諾曼  你想干什么
Norman, what do you think you're doing?
別碰我  諾曼
Don't you touch me! Don't! Norman!
把我放下  放下我  我自己能走
Put me down! Put me down! I can walk on my own.
早上好  早上好
Good morning. Good morning.
早上好
Good morning.
如果您不介意  我們愿駕車帶您去那間旅館
We thought if you didn't mind, we'd drive out to that motel with you.
他已經去過了
He's already been.
在儀式之前離開的
Went out before service.
你們倆吃過早餐了嗎
Did you two have breakfast?
什么也沒發現嗎
You didn't find anything?
沒有  我們別擋道
Nothing. Let's clear the way here.
他說了什么關于我妹妹的事嗎
Well, what did he say about my sister?
和他向你的偵探說的一樣  她用了匿名
Just what he told your detective, she used a fake name.
我看過了登記簿
Saw the register myself.
看過了整個地方  事實上  那小伙子一個人住在那兒
Saw the whole place, as a matter of fact. That boy's alone there.
他母親不在嗎
No mother?
肯定是你的幻覺  薩姆
You must have seen an illusion, Sam.
我知道你不會產生幻覺
I know you're not the seeing illusion's type,
但那兒沒有女人  而且我不相信鬼神之說
But no woman was there and I don't believe in ghosts,
-就是這樣  -我仍然覺得那兒有...
- So there it is. - I still feel that there's something...
我理解你的感受  很抱歉不能讓你好受些
Can see you do. I'm sorry l couldn't make you feel better.
你今天下午來我辦公室
You want to come around to my office this afternoon
填一份失蹤人口及遭遇搶劫的報告  這才是你要做的
And report a missing person and a theft, that's what you want to do.
你越快把此事交由法辦
The sooner you drop this in the lap of the law,
就越有可能快點找到你妹妹
That's the sooner you stand a chance of your sister being picked up.
怎么樣
How about that?
我不知道
I don't know.
今天是周日
It's Sunday.
晚飯時來我家填報告吧
Come on over to the house and do your reporting around dinnertime.
這樣會比較好
It'll make it nicer.
你也來吧  薩姆
You too, Sam.
謝謝
Thank you.
也許我真的會產生幻覺
Maybe I am the seeing illusions type.
不  你不會
No, you're not.
好吧  你想讓我把你送回旅館還是...
Well, you want me to drop you at the hotel or...
薩姆
Sam.
在沒親自去過那里之前  我不會罷休的
I still won't feel satisfied until I go out there.
我也不會  走吧
Neither will I. Come on.
我們最好想想到了那兒要怎么做
We better decide what we're gonna say or do when we walk in there.
我們先去注冊結婚
We're going to register as man and wife.
再去他那兒租間房
We're going to get shown to a cabin,
之后我們要調查那兒的每個角落  從里到外
And then we're going to search every inch of the place, inside and out.
我想知道諾曼﹒貝茨在哪兒隱居
I wonder where Norman Bates does his hermiting.
有人在窗戶那兒  我看到窗帘動了
Someone's at that window. I just saw the curtain move.
過來
Come on.
什么事
Well?
正想給你打電話
Just coming up to ring for you.
我猜你們想住店
Suppose you want a room.
我們本想直接去舊金山
We were gonna try to make it straight to San Francisco,
但是我們看了看天
But we don't like the look of that sky.
感覺馬上要變天了  對吧
Looks like a bad day coming, doesn't it?
好吧
Okay.
我帶你們去10號房間
I'll take you to cabin 10.
我們最好還是先登記  對吧
Better sign in first, hadn't we?
不  沒必要
No. That's not necessary.
我的老板會為此次旅行買單  90%可以報銷
My boss is paying for this trip and, well, it's 90% business.
但他需要正式發票
He wants practically notarized receipts.
我們最好登記  并拿到發票
I'd better sign in and get a receipt.
謝謝
Thank you.
-我幫你們去拿行李  -我們沒行李
- I'll get your bags. - Haven't any.
那我帶你們看一下房間
I'll show you the room, then.
頭回看到你這么開旅店
First time I've ever seen it happen.
在美國的其他旅店  沒有行李的旅客必須登記
You check in any other place in this country without bags
而且要付定金
And you have to pay in advance.
10美元
$10.
我的發票
That receipt.
我先去看看
I'll go on ahead.
好了  這是您的發票  那么  我來給您帶路
All right, there's your receipt. Now, I'll show you the cabin.
不麻煩了  我們自己能找到
Don't bother yourself. We'll find it.
薩姆  我們必須去調查那個房間
Sam, we have to go into that cabin and search it,
無論我們多么害怕  或者付出多大代價
No matter what we're afraid of finding or how much it may hurt.
知道了
I know.
如果真有事  你覺得那兒會是事發地點嗎
Do you think if something happened, it happened there?
我不知道
I don't know.
但如果你有一家這樣不賺錢的旅店
But if you had a useless business like this motel,
需要什么把它脫手
What would you need to get out?
然后在別的地方再開一家新的呢
To get a new business somewhere else?
4萬塊錢?
$40,000?
你如何証明這點
How could we prove that...
如果他在新高速路上開了家汽車旅店  一年后...
Well, if he opens a motel on the new highway in, say, a year...
這兒一定有証據
There must be some proof that exists now,
一定有能証明他搶走了曼璐錢的証據
Something that proves he got that money away from Marion somehow.
你憑什么那么肯定
What makes you sound so certain?
阿伯蓋斯特  她喜歡我  薩姆
Arbogast. He liked me, Sam.
或者他對我感到愧疚  對你
Or he felt sorry for me and he was
他亦是如此
Beginning to feel the same way about you.
從上次和他通話就可以証明
I could tell the last time I talked to him on the phone.
在去任何地方  或是作任何事情前
He wouldn't have gone anywhere
他一定會通知我們  除非有人阻止了他
Or done anything without telling us, unless he was stopped.
如果有人阻止了他  說明他一定發現了什么
And he was stopped. So he must have found out something.
我們從1號房間開始調查
We'll start with cabin one.
如果他看到我們  咱們就假裝在散步
If he sees us, we're just taking the air.
貝茨
Bates.
-沒有浴帘  -薩姆
- No shower curtain. - Sam!
看  這是什么
Look! What is it?
是數字  它沒被沖掉  看
It's figuring. It didn't get washed down. Look.
一些數字是用4萬加減得來的
Some figure has been added to or subtracted from 40,000.
這証明曼璐來過這兒
That proves Marion was here.
這太巧了
It'd be too wild a coincidence...
貝茨從未否認她來過這兒
Bates never denied she was here.
這不能証明他找到了那些錢嗎
Well, doesn't that prove that he found out about the money?
我們要直接去問他把錢藏哪兒了嗎
Do we simply ask him where he's hidden it?
不
No.
但那老婦人  無論她是誰  她曾告訴過阿伯蓋斯特一些事
But that old woman, whoever she is, she told Arbogast something.
我想讓她也把那些告訴我們
I want her to tell us the same thing.
你不能上去
You can't go up there.
為什么
Why not?
-因為貝茨  -那我們去找他
- Bates. - Well, let's find him.
我們其中一人把他穩住  另一人去找那位老婦人
One of us can keep him occupied while the other gets to the old woman.
如果他不愿意　你一定穩不住他
You'll never be able to hold him still if he doesn't want to be held.
我不想讓你獨自去他的房間
I don't like you going into that house alone.
但我能應付那個老病婦
I can handle a sick old woman.
好吧　我去把貝茨穩住
All right, I'll find bates and keep him occupied.
等等
Wait a minute.
如果你從那婦人嘴里得知了什么后
If you get anything out of the mother,
能找到回城的路嗎
Can you find your way back to town?
是的　當然
Yes, of course.
如果你真的得到了重要証據　不必來通知我
If you do get anything, don't stop to tell me.
你在找我嗎
You looking for me?
-什么事　-是的　事實上
- Why - Yes, as a matter of fact.
我的妻子在睡覺
Wife's taking a nap
但我可能會吵到她
And I never can keep quiet enough for her,
所以我來找你聊聊天
So I just thought I'd look you up and talk.
很好　你對房間還滿意嗎
Good. You satisfied with your cabin?
很好
Oh, it's fine.
這么半天　都是我在講話　對吧
I've been doing all the talking so far, haven't I?
我原本認為總是獨處的人
I thought it was the people who were alone most of the time
一旦有談話的機會　會滔滔不絕
Who did all the talking when they got the chance.
而你卻一言不發
Here you are doing all the listening.
你一個人住在這兒　對吧
You are alone here, aren't you?
這會讓我發瘋的
Drive me crazy.
我覺得你的反應太極端了　對吧
I think that would be a rather extreme reaction, don't you?
這只是種修辭手法
Just an expression.
我是說　無論如何我也會離開
What I meant was I'd do just about anything to get away.
-你不會嗎　-不會
- Wouldn't you? - No.
貝茨太太?
Mrs. Bates?
我不是說你住在這里不應該感到滿足
I'm not saying you shouldn't be contented here,
我只是不敢相信你會很滿足
I'm just doubting that you are.
我覺得如果你有機會擺脫困境  你肯定會
I think if you saw a chance to get out from under, you.
把這旅店脫手
Do unload this place.
這里嗎  這旅店是我的全部
This place? This place happens to be my only world.
我在這里長大  在這里度過了快樂的童年
I grew up in that house up there. I had a very happy childhood.
我和母親生活的非常幸福
My mother and I were more than happy.
你害怕了  是我的話讓你害怕了嗎
You look frightened. Have I been saying something frightening?
我不知道你在說些什么
I don't know what you.ve been saying.
我在說你母親  還有你的汽車旅館
I've been talking about your mother, about your motel.
你要如何處理它
How you gonna do it?
處理什么
Do what?
去個新地方再買一家嗎  這樣你就不必藏起你的母親了
Buy a new one in a new town where you won't have to hide your mother.
請你立刻開車離開這兒  好嗎
Why don't you just get in your car and drive away from here, okay?
你哪兒來的錢去做那些  貝茨
Where will you get the money to do that, Bates?
你是否已經把錢存起來了
Or do you already have it socked away?
閉嘴
Shut up!
很多錢  4萬塊錢
A lot of it. $40,000.
我打賭你媽媽知道錢在哪兒  也知道錢是怎么來的
I bet your mother knows where the money is and what you did to get it.
我想她會告訴我們的
I think she'll tell us.
跟你一起來的女孩呢  她在哪兒
Where's that girl you came here with? Where is she?
貝茨太太
Mrs. Bates...
我就是諾曼﹒貝茨
I'm Norman Bates!
如果誰能猜到答案  那他一定能當心理學家了
If anyone gets any answers it'll be the psychiatrist.
就連我也搞不懂他  而且他還認識我
Even I couldn't get to Norman and he knows me.
-你不冷嗎  小姐  -不冷
- You warm enough, miss? - Yes.
他跟你談過了嗎
Did he talk to you?
沒有
No.
我得知了一切  但不是從諾曼那里  是從他媽媽那兒
I got the whole story, but not from Norman. I got it from his mother.
諾曼﹒貝茨已經不存在了
Norman Bates no longer exists.
他本來還有一半尚存
He only half existed to begin with.
現在另一半完全占據了他
And now the other half has taken over,
或許一直如此
Probably for all time.
是他殺了我妹妹嗎
Did he kill my sister?
是
Yes.
也不是
And no.
聽著  如果你想為我們打精神病學的鋪墊
Well, now look, if you're trying to lay some psychiatric groundwork
這位伙計更愿意去抓...
For some sort of plea, this fellow would like to cop...
精神病學家不做任何鋪墊
A psychiatrist doesn't lay the groundwork.
他們僅僅想解釋緣由
He merely tries to explain it.
-但我妹妹...  -是啊
- But my sister is... - Yes.
是啊  我很遺憾
Yes, I'm sorry.
你的私家偵探也很遺憾
The private investigator, too.
如果你去調查汽車旅館附近的沼澤  你就會...
If you drag that swamp somewhere in the vicinity of the motel, you'll...
你是否有失蹤人口案件仍然在冊
Have you any unsolved missing persons cases on your books?
是的  有兩個
Yes, two.
都是年輕女孩嗎
Young girls?
他是不是已經承認...
Did he confess to...
-就像我說的  -那位母親
- Like I said, - The mother.
現在  我從他母親那兒得到信息的方式是這樣的
Now, to understand it the way I understood it, hearing it from the mother,
說道諾曼人格中母親的那部分
That is, from the mother half of Norman's mind,
我們須從10年前談起
You have to go back 10 years
那時  諾曼殺了他的母親及她的情人
To the time when Norman murdered his mother and her lover.
自從他父親去世后
Now, he was already dangerously disturbed,
他的精神就極度紊亂了
Had been ever since his father died.
他的母親  是一位執著而且苛刻的女性
His mother was a clinging, demanding woman,
他們兩個多年來就好像生活在
And for years the two of them lived
沒有其他人的世界里
As if there was no one else in the world.
然后  她愛上了一個男人
Then she met a man,
對于諾曼  感覺就像她為了那個男人把自己拋棄了
And it seemed to Norman that she threw him over for this man.
這讓他無法忍受  最終將二人全部殺死
Now, that pushed him over the line and he killed them both.
弒母大概是最無法令人忍受的犯罪了
Matricide is probably the most unbearable crime of all,
尤其是兒子親手殺了母親
Most unbearable to the son who commits it.
因此  他必須洗清罪惡  至少在他的思想中要這樣
So he had to erase the crime, at least in his own mind.
他偷走了她的尸體
He stole her corpse.
棺材下葬時裝的是其他重物
A weighted coffin was buried.
他把尸體藏在了果窖
He hid the body in the fruit cellar,
并十分妥善地保存著它
Even treated it to keep it as well as it would keep.
但這還不夠
And that still wasn't enough.
她人雖在那里  但卻成了一具尸體
She was there, but she was a corpse.
所以他開始以母親的方式思考  說話
So he began to think and speak for her,
可以說  他把自己的一半給了他母親
Give her half his life, so to speak.
有時  他的兩種人格同時存在  可以形成對話
At times he could be both personalities, carry on conversations.
而其他的時候  他母親的人格完全占據了他
At other times, the mother half took over completely.
他再也不完全是諾曼了  大部分時間他是自己的母親
He was never all Norman, but he was often only mother,
因為他是如此病態地妒忌著自己的母親
And because he was so pathologically jealous of her,
所以他認為母親也同樣妒忌著他
He assumed that she was as jealous of him.
因此  如果他被其他女人深深吸引
Therefore, if he felt a strong attraction to any other woman,
他"母親"的一面就會發狂
The mother side of him would go wild.
當他遇到你妹妹時
When he met your sister,
就被她深深觸動  深深吸引
He was touched by her, aroused by her.
他想要她
He wanted her.
這激怒了他"母親"的一面  然后他"母親"殺了那姑娘
That set off the jealous mother, and mother killed the girl.
殺完人后  諾曼如夢方醒
After the murder, Norman returned as if from a deep sleep,
變回了那個忠誠的兒子  并掩蓋掉一切罪行
And, like a dutiful son, covered up all traces of the crime
他確信殺人的是他母親
He was convinced his mother had committed!
他為什么要穿成那樣
Why was he dressed like that?
他是個異裝癖
He's a transvestite.
并不確切
Not exactly.
為了達到改變性別或者自我滿足
A man who dresses in women's clothing in order to achieve a sexual change
而穿上女人服飾的男人被稱作異裝癖
Or satisfaction is a transvestite.
但對于諾曼而言  他只是想竭盡全力去維持
But in Norman's case, he was simply doing everything possible
自己母親還活著的這一幻覺
To keep alive the illusion of his mother being alive.
而當現實逼近時
And when reality came too close,
當危險或者欲望要吞噬這個幻覺時
When danger or desire threatened that illusion,
他就會穿上女人服飾  甚至戴上假發
He'd dress up, even to a cheap wig he bought.
在屋子里徘徊  坐在母親的椅子上  用母親的腔調說話
He'd walk about the house, sit in her chair, speak in her voice.
他試著成為自己的母親
He tried to be his mother.
現在  他做到了
And now he is.
這就是我說  是從他母親那里得知一切的原因
That's what I meant when I said I got the story from the mother.
當人們腦海中出現雙重人格時
You see, when the mind houses two personalities,
就一定會有沖突  甚至戰爭
There's always a conflict, a battle.
對于諾曼而言  戰爭已經結束
In Norman's case, the battle is over,
較為強勢的人格獲勝
And the dominant personality has won.
那4萬塊錢呢  誰拿走了
And the $40,000? Who got that?
在沼澤里  這次犯罪源于人格分裂  而非圖財
The swamp. These were crimes of passion, not profit.
他覺得有點冷  我能把毯子給他嗎
He feels a little chill. Can I bring him this blanket?
當然  可以
Oh, sure. All right.
謝謝
Thank you.
當一位母親不得不譴責自己的兒子時
It's sad when a mother has to speak the words
是多么悲哀啊
That condemn her own son,
但我不會讓他們認為是我殺的人
But I couldn't allow them to believe that I would commit murder,
他們會拋棄他的  就像我數年前應該做的那樣
They'll put him away now, as I should have years ago,
他一向很壞
He was always bad,
最終  他打算告訴警察是我殺的那些女孩和那個男人
And in the end he intended to tell them I killed those girls and that man,
除了端坐和凝視外  我什么也做不了
As if I could do anything except just sit and stare,
就像他的標本鳥一樣
Like one of his stuffed birds,
他們知道  我連手指都動不了  而且我也不會
They know I can't even move a finger, and I won't,
我只會在這里靜靜端坐  以免被人懷疑
I'll just sit here and be quiet, just in case they do suspect me,
他們大概會監視我  好吧  讓他們看吧
They're probably watching me, well, let them,
讓他們看看我是什么樣的人
Let them see what kind of a person I am,
我甚至不會拍死這只蒼蠅
I'm not even gonna swat that fly,
我希望他們在監視我  他們就會看到
I hope they are watching, they'll see,
他們會看到并且明白
They'll see and they'll know,
之后  他們會說"為什么  她連蒼蠅都不愿傷害啊"
And they'll say, ''why, she wouldn't even harm a fly, ''